<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Just an Angle]]></title>
  <subtitle><![CDATA[A collection of Perspectives]]></subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://justangle.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-27T06:33:00.000Z</updated>
  <id>http://justangle.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Arun Balakrishnan, Shivakumar D]]></name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[In light of the surfeit of 'logic' floating around]]></title>
    <link href="http://justangle.com/2016/07/26/convenient-isnt-it/"/>
    <id>http://justangle.com/2016/07/26/convenient-isnt-it/</id>
    <published>2016-07-26T18:33:12.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-27T06:33:00.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/convenient_perception1.jpg" alt=""><br>The omnipotent and infinite lord, is formless. He does not have any form………… Isn’t there an inherent contradiction in that?</p>
<p>The Lord is omnipotent generally, but is impotent to assume a form? And the Lord, whose limits we fix in finite terms, is infinite?</p>
<p>The moment we limit the possibilities of what the Lord can or cannot, we reduce the Lord to finite and definite. Conversely, how can one fathom infinity to go so far as to constrain it?</p>
<p>Either emphatic assertion, that he is only with form or the one that precludes form are both logically limiting. As Sri Ramakrishna used to say, when in the gaseous state, H2O has no form; in the liquid state, it is free flowing and in the solid state, it simply takes the shape of the container.</p>
<p>Let’s make an allowance for both, but what is the point worshipping a stone or wooden image? Does idol worship ever make sense? Well, the idol itself is never the target or object of worship.</p>
<p>In course of his travels, Swami Vivekananda reached Alwar and was accosted by the king Mangal Singh. The Maharaja asked him, “I find the image-worship you people engage in meaningless. Why would anyone want to worship clay, metal or stone?” Swami Vivekananda looked around and saw a painting of the king’s father hanging on the wall, and requested that it be brought down to him. He then asked the king to spit on it. The king was infuriated and burst out “How can I spit on my father? What guts should you have to seek it!” Swami Vivekananda exclaimed, “But where is your father here? Isn’t it paint and paper?” The king was tongue tied, it was his own logic after all. Swami Vivekananda then went on to explain that the idol is simply meant to remind the worshipper of the principle it symbolized or represented. All worship offered, was to the Being it reminded of and not itself.</p>
<p>But why leave room for form and formless, and on top of it multiple forms? A “one-size-fits-all” approach wouldn’t really benefit everybody. If the only shop in town that sold clothes, had only one size? And only one pattern and colour? Would it suit everybody? The contemplation, comprehension and assimilation levels vary between people, just as physiques do. He chooses that form that is conducive to his state.</p>
<p>Doesn’t it mean there are many Gods that get worshipped? There are cookies shaped as a key, a bird, a house etc. Children fight over them, with one choosing a house and another a key. Does it mean that each child is eating many different biscuits? Forms vary, but the fundamental substance remains the same. To the child, a particular form beckons. So also, to the worshipper. All rivers finally culminate in the ocean.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/convenient_perception1.jpg" alt=""><br>The omnipotent and infinite lord, is formless. He does not have any form………… Isn]]>
    </summary>
    
      <category term="god" scheme="http://justangle.com/tags/god/"/>
    
      <category term="omnipotence" scheme="http://justangle.com/tags/omnipotence/"/>
    
      <category term="Spiritual" scheme="http://justangle.com/categories/Spiritual/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Rajya Sabha Impasse, Is Money Bill the Answer?]]></title>
    <link href="http://justangle.com/2015/12/15/Rajya-Sabha-Impasse-Is-Money-Bill-the-Answer/"/>
    <id>http://justangle.com/2015/12/15/Rajya-Sabha-Impasse-Is-Money-Bill-the-Answer/</id>
    <published>2015-12-14T23:29:38.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-07-26T18:51:49.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/RSabha_nostalgic.jpg" alt=""><br>“<strong>Fools rush in, where angels fear to tread</strong>”, it is said. A draconian law like <strong>Section 66A</strong> of the IT Act, was passed by the Rajya Sabha (not just the Lok Sabha) without so much as a sneeze, cough or murmur. Contrast this with the Rajya Sabha’s united ambush against something totally perfunctory and inconsequential, as an amendment to the motion of thanks to the President’s address! The effect? A few words added and the paper dumped into some bin. But going by their seriousness, one would have thought the nation’s very existence hung on it. Other than embarrassing the government, it would serve no other purpose. Indeed it seemed that some members had no other purpose. When essential businesses are held ransom to such petty behavior by a few (who seem to have infinite time for leisure and mischief), what is the way out?</p>
<p>Currently important legislations sail through the Lok Sabha and then may go into what could possibly be a dead end or black hole (select committee of the Rajya Sabha). Essential reforms introduced by representatives directly elected by the people, are blocked by a house that provides for (with due respect) back door entry. In a bicameral legislature like India, the general rule is that a bill becomes law once both the houses of the parliament pass it. But impasse sets in when one proposes, and the other disposes. Can the nation afford this absurd game?</p>
<p>Certainly not. And the central govt. seems to agree, as it explores the “money bill” route to circumvent these mindless opposition. While there is no definitive solution to this cat and mouse game, the constitution thankfully exempts “money bills” from this acrimonious farce. The money bill route definitely gives some respite, albeit limited, as it has the following peculiarities:</p>
<ul>
<li>A money bill can only be introduced in the Lok Sabha (unlike the other bills). The Lok Sabha Speaker’s stamp, certifying a bill as a “money bill” is final, and not open to anybody’s question, even the courts cannot interfere.</li>
<li>The Rajya Sabha has to vote on the money bill passed by the Lok Sabha and return within 14 days. The recommendations of the Rajya Sabha are not binding, and the Lok Sabha may choose to pass the bill in its original form.</li>
<li>If the Rajya Sabha fails to vote on it within 14 days, the bill is deemed to be passed!</li>
<li>It cannot be referred to a Joint Committee of the houses, thereby precluding intentional stalling.</li>
</ul>
<p>While this might seem a wonderful panacea, it may be noted that not all businesses can be transacted as a money bill. What then is a money bill? Article 110 of the Constitution describes the purposes, to address which a money bill is resorted to. A money bill is one that seeks to (any of the following):</p>
<ul>
<li>Levy any tax or abolish, modify the same (any tax like income tax, customs duty etc)</li>
<li>Administer the flows of Consolidated Fund of India, and the expenditures from it (Consolidated Fund is the ocean into which all the govt.’s loans, the taxes collected from you etc. flow).</li>
<li>Regulate any borrowing by the Central Govt., or any financial obligation to be incurred by it.</li>
<li>Public money and it’s audit in case of accounts of State / Central govt</li>
<li>Issues incidental to the above.</li>
</ul>
<p>The term incidental is rather deceptive! It can be wide enough to go beyond the usual routine such as tax rates and the subject matter of taxation, and touch upon machinery, mechanisms &amp; methods as well. At the same time, a bill does not become a money bill merely for the reason it encompasses fees and fines. Hunt with the hounds and run with the hares, eh?</p>
<p>As can be seen, only issues which fall in the above realm can be passed as a money bill. The black money bill was one such example, where the bill sailed through the Rajya Sabha. The antagonists were left gnashing their teeth, as they wanted to stall it by referring to the Standing Committee (aka the black hole committee).</p>
<p>Goods and Service Tax (GST), which seeks to bring about a unified tax regime is a much sought after reform, and the govt. is pushing it really hard. What prevents the GST bill from being passed as a money bill? Unfortunately it needs an amendment of the constitution, and constitutional amendment bills cannot be classified as money bills, even if it addresses the above issues. So, such barriers will continue till such time our leaders rise above petty considerations, and worry about the nation.</p>
<p>Some possible solutions that could possibly solve the issue:</p>
<ul>
<li>Abolition of whips (Whips are orders issued by a political party that binds all members to stick to a particular stand, failing which they risk expulsion). Conscientious voting by members could perhaps see different results.</li>
<li>Trifurcation of representation in the Rajya Sabha among States, group of professionals &amp; domain experts and the ruling group. This way, a majority can be forged where the proposition is reasonable.</li>
<li>Representation of the states be made truly representative of the people’s will of the day. This can be ensured by making representation co-terminus and ex-officio with the tenure of the state legislative assemblies. Currently, the newly elected assemblies get their representation years after they get elected.</li>
<li>Legislating a fixed period for select committees to give their recommendations, ensuring they don’t become black holes.</li>
<li>Some of the seats can be directly elected by the people, and qualifications prescribed for contestants (such as high specializations in fields of finance, medicine, technology etc).</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/RSabha_nostalgic.jpg" alt=""><br>“<strong>Fools rush in, where angels fear to tread</strong>”, it is said. A draconian ]]>
    </summary>
    
      <category term="politics" scheme="http://justangle.com/tags/politics/"/>
    
      <category term="rajya sabha" scheme="http://justangle.com/tags/rajya-sabha/"/>
    
      <category term="Politics" scheme="http://justangle.com/categories/Politics/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
